STD expected. A phrase I have never said
before and probably never will again. In
fact, I might break my rule and say
standard instead of std today. So, C++
23 has finally introduced something that
I think is actually a strong way of
dealing with errors properly in C++.
Now, we're going to spend the rest of
this video talking about this, but
before we do, let me just cut to the
chase and show you what it is. Say, for
example, you have a function that needs
to divide two integers. There's a
possibility that that second integer
could be zero. And if it is, that's an
error. What expected allows you to do is
return two possible results. Either the
actual result if the function succeeds
or an error result. So you can see here
that we take in two integers A and B,
but if B is zero, we instead return an
unexpected result which is going to be
of this type. Otherwise, we do the
division and we return the result of
that as an integer. The caller receives
this expected object and can check
whether or not it's valid. That is to
say whether or not we actually have the
result because it succeeded or we get
the unexpected result. If it is valid
then we can use it however we like such
as printing it in this case. But if it's
not valid then we can retrieve the error
which in this case is a string and do
what we will with it. So for this
example I'm trying to divide 10 by two.
If I run this code then as you might
expect we print result equals 5 because
that's what we're doing over here.
However, if I change this to be zero,
which is invalid, then instead we're
getting a divide by zero error, which is
what we set our unexpected object to.
So, in a nutshell, that is what expected
is. It allows you to either return one
value or another based on whatever
conditions you define. The way this
works internally is very important
because of course, we care about what
our code is actually doing and
performance. So internally an expected
object is actually a union of either the
success value or the unexpected value
plus one additional bite which basically
dictates whether or not it's this value
or that value. That's it. So depending
of course on what types you actually put
into these template arguments. The
expected class itself does not allocate
any memory and it stores its data very
very simply which basically means that
the overhead for this should be almost
zero. And that's important because in my
opinion that actually makes this quite
useful and that's what we're going to
talk about for the rest of this video.
Now if you are just getting into
programming and you want a really fun
and engaging way to learn then bootdev
the sponsor of this video is the perfect
thing for you. Bootdev takes inspiration
from modern game design to teach
programming in a super fun and engaging
way. They specifically focus on back-end
development but these concepts apply to
any language and any type of
development. The most important thing
when learning programming is that you
actually practice that you actually
write code. If you're just watching
videos or learning theory without
practice, then you're not really
learning. Bootdev actually has you
writing code from the very beginning and
in a super fun and engaging way. You'll
earn XP, complete quests, level up, talk
to your bear mentor, who wants salmon as
payment, all while writing code
yourself, fixing bugs, and really just
being a real developer. Now, this bear
mentor is an AI chatbot specifically
trained on their course materials. So,
if you get stuck or you want a deeper
explanation of something, then you can
always have a chat with it. But check
this out. All of their content is
completely free to read and watch in
guest mode, so you can always check it
out first. You'll need a paid membership
to access the interactive features like
hands-on programming. There's lots more
to discover, so head to boot.dev, link
will be in description below, and check
it out for yourselves. You can also use
code churn to get 25% off your entire
first year if you choose the annual
plan. Huge thank you to bootdev for
sponsoring this video. Okay, so let's
kind of go back to the beginning and
talk about this in much more detail. So
first and foremost, you need to make
sure that you are on C++ 23. So in
Visual Studio, for example, you would go
to your project properties, make sure
you're in all configurations, and then
under C, C++, and language, you need to
make sure that you are I mean, as of I
mean, I think I updated Visual Studio
like during June 2025 or something. This
is still marked as preview, but you can
see we have C++ 23 preview here. Just
make sure you are using either C++ 23
preview or it's also possible if you're
on an older version of Visual Studio but
not too old. You might have to select
preview features from latest C++ working
draft. But anyway, I recommend you
update Visual Studio and you just select
C++ 23 here. If you're using any other
IDE or something like CMake or Premake,
you can also set the same setting there.
But you just need to make sure that you
are on C++ 23 because this is a C++ 23
feature. As is the print line function
which we discussed in the last C++ video
which I will leave linked up there. So
once we are sure that we are in fact
using C++ 23, let's go ahead and include
expected. So what I'm going to do here
is I'm just going to implement this
divide function that we just wrote. So
we're going to divide a by b. Usually
you'd write something like this. We of
course have the risk of actually
dividing by zero here. Let's say we want
to handle that error. That's reasonable.
And by the way, yes, this function is a
little bit silly. No one really most the
time writes functions like this, but
this is a metaphor. This is supposed to
represent a real function in a very
simple way because we're not focusing on
the function itself. We're focusing on
this kind of error code flow
functionality. So without something like
expected, how would we handle the case
of dividing by zero? Well, I think that
probably most people would do something
like throw an exception. Now, I'm not
the biggest fan of exceptions. They're
definitely fine to use. In fact, I
haven't made a single video about them.
That's how you know I'm not the biggest
fan of them. Objectively, they are not
that bad. However, from a code flow
point of view, I still am not the
biggest fan of them because once you
throw an exception over here, you then
obviously need to do a try catch block
and it just becomes very messy. Okay, so
let's just say we don't want to use
exceptions. What other options do we
have? Well, instead of returning an int
here, we might instead return some kind
of like status code. And then maybe the
result would be like, you know, some
kind of output parameter here that we
would set. And then this status which
I'm trying to write as fast as possible
could be something like I don't know
success divide by zero. This at least
gives you like some context as to what
goes wrong compared to if we had just
returned a boolean but obviously
returning a boolean is also fine. In
fact I probably should have started with
that but anyway so divide by zero we can
just say not do the division obviously
and return status divide by zero. I
guess error makes sense. Another way to
deal with this may have been to actually
make something like error and then have
this be none. This probably makes more
sense. And then divide by zero. And
there you go. You have to return either
error none or erroride by zero. Then
from the calling code, this becomes a
little bit annoying. So we have our
result from the division of let's just
say 10 x two. You can see ah hang on a
minute. That's not the result. That's
the error status. The result is actually
something that we have to store up here
which I already don't like. And then we
have to check if error status equals
none hopefully. And then if it is none
then we can use our result for whatever
we want such as printing it. Otherwise
we have to deal with it there. So I mean
I'm not a fan of this. Admittedly an
easier way for something as simple as
this might have been to use a boolean.
So if we just have bull divide I mean
this is pretty black and white. Either
the division worked or it didn't. In
more complicated examples, which we will
get into later in this video, you might
have something like reading a file.
Reading a file might go wrong for a
number of different reasons. Maybe the
file doesn't exist. Maybe the buffer
you've provided to read the file is too
small. Maybe the file is already open
for reading and you can't obtain a lock
on it. Maybe you don't have access to
read that particular file. There are so
many things that could go wrong there
that obviously returning a simple
boolean doesn't cut it. But in this
example, for the simple things in life,
we can probably just return a boolean.
So if this is the case, then we can
return false. Otherwise, let's just
output our out result and return true.
That does clean up the code a little bit
because we don't have to do all of this
enum checking. We can just simply put
this into the if block itself and then
we have the result to deal with. Again,
this works great in very, very simple
cases, aside from, you know, the fact
that we have this result here. But to be
honest, this is probably the best thing
we have built into C++ without using
expected. So now that we have expected,
let's rewrite this to use expected and
then see if we like it better. So
instead of returning a boolean, we're
going to return an expected object of
either an integer or in this case we can
just stick to our boolean. Now the best
thing about this probably already is
that we don't need this out result. That
gets removed because the result is
actually in the object we're returning.
So if B is zero then we can return
unexpected and of course it's going to
be of this type otherwise we just simply
return this and that's it. We don't need
to wrap it in an expected there's an
implicit constructor for us. So then
over here in the calling code this
changes a little bit. You store the
result up here usually as an auto
object. The type is this but because
this is kind of long usually we would
just use auto. This is gone which is
great. Keeps our function really clean
looking. And then we can simply check to
see if the result is valid or not. If we
have a result. There is also a has value
function. But that is what this operator
bull does for us. And then to use it, we
use like this dreference kind of
operator to get the value. Or we can of
course use value. Now in this case we
actually don't care about the error
value because we are just storing a bull
and that bull kind of reflects whether
or not this is unexpected or expected
which is what this bull operator in the
expected object itself actually does for
us. So the data here is meaningless like
we probably wouldn't actually want to
retrieve error because in this case we
know error is going to be false. False
is the only possible error value that we
return. So we can just assume that it's
false. But this is how you would
retrieve error. Now note that retrieving
value and retrieving error is not valid.
You can't call these functions. They
will throw exceptions if result is not
valid and you call value or result is
valid and you call error. So basically
you need to check what this is first
before you can call value or use the
dreference operator and before you call
error. Now how is this different than if
we had just returned two values. So
let's say we had a strct divide return
result which already you've lost me at
this but anyway let's bear with it. So
we have either our result or a boolean.
Well this actually would not be any
different in this case. So what we could
do is not care about setting result but
instead just return something like zero
and false. Otherwise we could return the
division and true. If you get a little
bit clever with this and you return a
bull operator which simply returns a
then this actually becomes somewhat
reasonable. You have your result. You
can check result like this. And then you
simply access the result. And again, if
you wanted that same functionality, you
could also have int operator this thing
and then have it return result. And then
check this out. We have the same exact
functionality except obviously instead
of error. I mean obviously you could
implement the dot error function and
just return a, but we basically have the
same functionality. Now the reason why
is because this just stores an int and a
bull, both of them in memory. Four bytes
plus an additional bite. We have five
bytes effectively of this packed strct
data that we are actually storing the
same as if we would have used expected
because remember expected also stores
that additional bull of whether or not
we have value. But what if we wanted to
store something a little bit more
complex such as a string for our error
value? Well, in this case, we're
actually storing an integer and then a
string. So, we're storing more data than
we need to. So, what if we use a union?
Well, you can probably see where we're
going with this. we'll use a union and
then we'll have to know is it result or
is it a so has value and we've basically
just written the expected class. So yes,
this is what it does except obviously
it's a template and it's not hardcoded
to be these two particular types. It can
be any type. So hopefully this gives you
a deeper understanding as to what
expected actually is and how it works.
Let's go back to int and string. I'll
return this divide by zero as an
unexpected result. And we can get rid of
this and return just the result. By the
way, if you want to return this with our
other strct that we made, you could of
course add a constructor that just takes
in this parameter. And as long as you
don't mark it explicit, then this code
will also compile. Okay, so the expected
class goes a little bit deeper than
this. But I think this simple use case
is probably going to be something that
most of you will use most of the time.
If we have a look at some of the more
advanced functions in there, the most
interesting things that you can actually
do with this is chain multiple expected
functions together. So if we wanted to
divide 10 by two and then depending on
the result potentially do another
division or run something else, then
once we do this, we can actually use
this and then function. I'll drop it
down here so it's a little bit cleaner.
This takes in a lambda which takes in
the result of this previous function and
specifically the true result the
successful result. So if we have our
division result and then we want to for
example divide again now and then note
that this lambda has to actually return
another expected function. There's
another function called transform that
doesn't but this one does. So let's say
for example we then take the result and
we divide it by two again. Maybe I'll
pick something like 12 and 3. So that'll
give us four and then we'll divide by
two. So we should get two. So I'll
return this and you can of course keep
chaining them. But what happens if the
expected function fails? What happens if
we get an unexpected result? Well,
that's where or else comes in. So and
then is what we do if it's successful or
else is what we do if it fails. And
these errors will propagate. Meaning
that if this one fails, we will land in
here. And if this one fails, then we
will also land in here. So in this case,
we are of course going to get that error
which I can take in as const reference
here. So we have our error and then
let's go ahead and just print it in this
case. Maybe I'll drop this down here.
We'll go ahead and print this. And this
also should return an expected. So what
we'll do is we'll go ahead and just
create this expected object. However,
I'm just going to set it to zero. So
this is basically going to be our
fallback value. So if these divisions
fail, let's just return zero and then
we'll wrap up this lambda. So now we are
actually building some kind of logic,
some kind of code flow in a very
functional style. We're trying to divide
12 by 3. If that succeeds, we are then
dividing the result of that which should
be four by two. Again, if either of them
fail, we are printing the error and
returning zero. Which means that at this
stage, we will always get a result.
We're not going to get an error at this
stage because we have this fallback
value and that result should be zero. So
let's go ahead and print that. If we run
this code, then the result is going to
be two because obviously all of these
succeed. But if I change one of these to
zero, then we're going to get this
divide by zero, but we're also going to
get a valid result of zero. And then, of
course, if this one is fine, but this
one is invalid and fails, then we're
going to get the exact same result.
We'll just get a divide by zero error
and our fallback value like that. You
can, of course, omit this and just not
have an or else, which means that you
can handle it at the actual calling
site. I mean this is also the calling
side but you can handle it later just
via a simple if statement in this case.
But this kind of chaining functionality
can be really useful if you want to
avoid all of these if statements because
you can imagine that if we wanted to do
something like this and just express it
as if statements which we obviously
could do we would have to do something
like this. So we're just dividing here
then if the result succeeds we're going
to want to do another division which is
this one over here. And then if that one
succeeds, then you know we can print the
result. For example, making sure it's
result two. You can see how as we keep
going more levels deep into this, we're
just going to end up creating this
massive if statement nest. And then what
about the else statements if they fail
at any point, right? Right? I mean,
honestly, at this rate, you almost would
rather use go-tos to actually get to
that or else condition because
otherwise, you're going to have to
somehow break out of all of these nested
if statements just to get to the point
where it says divide by zero error or
handles your error condition, which is
not good compared to this where you
simply have, you know, as many of these
as you want followed by a single place
that actually handles your what happens
if it fails condition. So this is
another really really strong use case I
would say for this whole expected
functionality and if you utilize this
properly then I think this is going to
be a huge improvement to the code flow
of your error handling. Now speaking of
utilizing this properly strings are not
something that I would realistically
probably return. You know they're great
for like little prototype functions or
just testing stuff out like I'm showing
you. But generally the power of this is
that you can return much more than a
string. Specifically you could return
any type. I mean, I would be careful to
make sure that that type, for example,
doesn't allocate memory and is trivally
copyable. You you don't want to like
have this huge thing necessarily,
especially if you care about
performance, obviously, but you could
have something that has much more
information than simply this. Now, I
think it's about time that we ditch this
simple example and instead, let's look
at how we might use expected in the
context of trying to read a file, for
example. Okay, so I got chatbt to
generate a fairly comprehensive and
thorough read file function which uses
expected. I did have to clean it up a
little bit admittedly, but to be honest,
not bad. Not bad. So this pretty much
handles every possible state. So first
and foremost, you can see we are
returning two things. We're returning
either a vector of chars or a file
error. Now file error is a strct that
has three different variables here. a
file error code, the path of the file
that is the error, and a string message.
It's also got this friend output
operator, which guess we don't really
use C out anymore, but you can see it's
got this operator here that just
converts this file error, which
definitely doesn't need to be taken in
as a const reference, but anyway, it
takes in takes in this file error enum
class here and just outputs a string.
So, it's kind of like a two-string
function for file error to just convert
this enum to a string so that you can
like print it. So this I would say is a
fairly good example of the kind of error
type you can actually return. Doesn't
have to just be a simple error code. It
could be an entire strct of data that
will definitely help you actually handle
your errors properly. Like for example,
the fact that this returns a path is
kind of important because if we go down
to the calling code, say for example, I
had a bunch of these like and then blah
blah blah and then at the end of them I
had an or else. Now remember or else is
going to take in that error strct,
right? But this or else kind of catches
any of the and then as well as the
original read file that might happen. So
we might not really be aware of which
one of these failed. But if you have
information such as that inside your
error type then obviously you can handle
that appropriately. Now going through
the way that this actually works is
pretty simple as you might imagine. If
for example the file just simply doesn't
exist then we can make an unexpected
object here that has our error type in
here. So we're creating an instance of
that strct with file not found as the
error code. The path obviously of the
file that happens for all of these. And
then in this case we're actually
outputting this message that comes from
these file system functions. This error
code which is like a platform specific
error code of what actually went wrong
for potential further diagnostics which
could be very useful if it's just not
not a file or there's a read failure or
the files even too large. It defines
like this 100 megabyte max asset file
size which of course is arbitrary.
That's just something that we might have
inside our asset system for whatever
reason. Then it's just too big for asset
loader is what it decides to print here.
Otherwise, it will open it as a binary
file here. We might not be able to. So,
we might get a permission denied in
which case we'll respond to that. And
then finally, we'll try and read it. But
then if there's a read failure, then we
also return an unexpected. Otherwise, we
simply return that vector which is our
buffer over here. Now, obviously from
the calling point of view, if we have
the result successfully, we're all good.
But if we don't, then we can just call
dot error. And then on that error, we
can check the code. We can print the
message. We can see which file failed.
In this case, we're only reading one, so
it's obviously this one. But you get the
point. And remember, because we have all
of those other functions here, we can
kind of get rid of these if statements
if you so choose. So, for example, if we
read the file and then we want to do
something with it, then in this case, we
could use the transform function. it'll
take in that data and then it might
actually pass on that data to our actual
asset loading system. And in this case,
we could just return the data because we
don't really care about it and we would
get that in the original object.
However, if it fails, we could of course
print that error or handle it however we
like. At this point, you may be slightly
confused as to what the difference
between transform and the and then
function is. Well, it's pretty simple.
And then has to return another expected
object. Technically, they actually both
return expected objects. So, the
clearest I can make the difference is
that and then can potentially also fail
using that expected system. Meaning that
it's perfect for if you want to say run
this function if that result succeeds,
but this can fail. All of the and thens
that you have in your chain can fail.
And if they do fail, then you wind up in
or else. However, transform is used for
things that cannot fail because you can
see I'm not calling that expected
function again. I'm actually just
returning this part of the expected
object, right? The success condition.
I'm not returning this error or
anything. I'm just doing something with
that result potentially and returning
just that first part of it. Whereas with
and then I'm doing something that might
also fail again and I want to wind up in
this or else. So in this scenario,
transform makes sense because I'm not
calling a function that returns expected
again. I'm not doing something that
might fail. I'm simply passing like the
data on and that's it. Whereas if I
wanted to do something else such as for
example pass that data and then maybe
that returns the expected result or an
error code and then I want to wind up in
here. If I had wanted to chain together
multiple expected calls here and then
handle any of them failing inside this
or else function then that's when I
would use and then. So hopefully you
guys enjoy this overview of expected in
C++ 23. Let me know what you think in
the comment section below. I personally
think this is actually a really really
good addition to C++ and something that
honestly you know if you have access to
C++ 23 and you are in fact using that
which you know if you're just working on
your own project especially if you're
starting a new project you should be
using C++ 23 then I would strongly
recommend that you use something like
this going forward. Let me know what you
guys want me to cover next in the
comments section below and I will see
you guys next time. Goodbye.